Gertrude Claus Collection of Goodall-Sanford, Inc., Photographs 6664 P
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
- Inspection and Development, 1952; black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Item 8: Full Decating, 1952; black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Gelatin silver print. Image depicts machinery used in the process of full decating fabric. Decating is a finishing process done on woolen and worsted fabrics to set the nap and develop the luster of the material. A male employee is visible behind the rolls of material. Text: "Full Decating. The fabric is put on a perforated roll under tension with a heavy cotton leader of sateen weave. This roll is placed into a cylinder which is hermetically sealed. The air is pumped out thus creating a vacuum. Then steam is injected and left on for several minutes. The roll is now allowed to cool and the fabric removed. This process sets the fabric and imparts a desiered luster." 25.5 x 20.5cm. (w/out mount); 27 x 20.5 cm. (w/mount).
  - Item 9: Semi Decating, 1952; black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Gelatin silver print. Image depicts machinery used in the process of semi decating fabric. Decating is a finishing process done on woolen and worsted fabrics to set the nap and develop the luster of the material. A male employee is partially visible on the right, somewhat hidden behind the machinery. Here the material is seen on large rollers under a hood. Text: "Semi Decating. The process is similar to that described for full decating, except that no vacuum is used. For certain types of fabric this treatment is preferred." See item 8 in this folde for a description of full decating. 25 x 20.5cm. (w/out mount); 27 x 20.5 cm. (w/mount).
  - Item 10: Final Inspection, 1952; black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Gelatin silver print. Image depicts two male employees inspecting fabric. The fabric is draped over a roller and drawn down by hand as they inspect for defects. Text: "Final Inspection. Before shipping, every yard of fabric must be carefully inspected to insure that it meets our high quality standards." 25 x 20.5 cm. (w/out mount); 27 x 20.5 cm. (w/mount).
  - Item 11: Yarn Development, 1952; black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Gelatin silver print. Image depicts a room where new machinery has been installed to investigate different spinning methods. Text: "Yarn Development. This shows installation of Pilot Plant machinery where different spinning methods are being investigated." 25.25 x 20.5 cm. (w/out mount); 27 x 20.5 cm. (w/mount).
  - Item 12: Product Development, 1952; black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Gelatin silver print. Image depicts a room with employees (all male) working on narrow looms, weaving sample pieces of fabric,. Text: "Product Development. Prior to full production runs, sample pieces are woven on narrow looms to insure that fabrics are correctly constructed for their respective end use." 25 x 20.5 cm. (w/out mount); 27 x 20.5 cm. (w/mount).
  - Item 13: Main Laboratory, 1952; black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Gelatin silver print. Image depicts the main laboratory. The view, taken from a slightly high perspective, shows a room with glassed-in cubicles, one of which holds a loom. Text: "Main Laboratory. This Laboratory is divided into several sections comprising Chemical Control Laboratory, Physical Control Laboratory, Chemical Research Laboratory, Dye Laboratory, Application Laboratory, Microscopic Laboratory, Physical Research Laboratory, and Color Fastness Laboratory. Tests are performed against rigid speciications; and all fabrics must meet these specifications, depending upon their end use." 25 x 20.5 cm. (w/out mount); 27 x 20.5 cm. (w/mount).
  - Item 14: Chemical Control Laboratory, 1952; black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Gelatin silver print. Image depicts a male employee at work in the chemical control laboratory. Man is wearing a white lab coat and dark pants, standing in front of a row of extractors. Text: "Chemical Control Laboratory. Here we see a bank of Soxhlet Extractors into which small samples of fiber are placed. The purpose of this test is to determine the amount of grease the intermediate products contain." See item 15 in this folder for a close-up view of these extractors. 25 x 20.5 cm. (w/out mount); 27 x 20.5 cm. (w/mount).
  - Item 15: Chemical Control Laboratory [Close-up View of Extractors], 1952; black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Gelatin silver print. Image depicts a close-up view of the Soxhlet Extractors seen in the prior image of the chemical control laboratory (item 14 in this folder). A male employee wearing a lab coat is behind the extractors, pouring ether into one of them. Text: "Chemical Control Laboratory. This is a close-up of these Soxhlet Extractors showing hot plates, beakers containing ether, and the Soxhlet tube through which this ether is repeatedly passed." 25 x 20.5 cm. (w/out mount); 27 x 20.5 cm. (w/mount).
  - Item 16: Chemical Laboratory, 1952; black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Gelatin silver print. Image depicts a male employee at work in a chemical laboratory. The employee wears a long white lab coat, and is standing in front of a table with a beaker of a chemical in front of him. A row of jars (presumably containing other chemicals) is on the shelf above the table. Text: "Chemical Laboratory. This is one of the Chemical Laboratories used in testing shipments of chemicals to determine if they meet purchasing specifications. We also test new chemical products to continually improve our processes and fabrics." 25.25 x 20.5 cm. (w/out mount); 27 x 21 cm. (w/mount).
  - Item 17: Physical Testing Laboratory, 1952; black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Gelatin silver print. Image depicts two female employees at work in the physical testing laboratory. Both employees wear white lab coats; one has her back to the camera and is involved with something against the wall; the other works on something on the table in the center of the room. The lettering on the door in the background reads "Conditioning Testing." Text: "Physical Testing Laboratory. This Laboratory has to be maintained at standard atmospheric condition, namely, 70 [degrees] F, 65% relative humidity. Because of the hygroscopic properties of fibers, humidity has an important effect on weight and strength. In order to enable us to obtain constant results, the testing room has to be air conditioned. Yarns are periodically tested for yarn size, twist and strength to maintain uniform quality standards and production requirements." 25 x 20.5 cm. (w/out mount); 27 x 20.5 cm. (w/mount).
  - Item 18: Calender Coating Operation, Reading [Mass.] Division, 1952; black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Gelatin silver print. Image depicts two male employees at work in the calender coating operation at the Reading, Mass., division of Goodall-Sanford, Inc., of Sanford, Me. The Reading division handled dyeing and finishing. Calendering is a cloth finishing process, whereby a fabric is pressed between rollers. In this case, a plastic film is being applied. Text: "Calender Coating Operation, Reading Division. This operation shows a cotton fabric being passed between the rolls of a plastic calender and having a film of plastic material pressed against the face of the cotton fabric under heat and pressure to secure a proper bond." 25 x 20.5 cm. (w/out mount); 27 x 20.5 cm. (w/mount).
  - Item 19: Plastic Printing, Reading [Mass.] Division, 1952; black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Gelatin silver print. Image depicts a male employee standing next to one of the printers in the plastic printing operations at the Reading, Mass., division of Goodall-Sanford, Inc., of Sanford, Me. The Reading division handled dyeing and finishing. Text: "Plastic Printing, Reading Division. This machine deposits a plastic ink, by means of an engraved roll, onto the surface of the plastic coated fabric." 25 x 20.5 cm. (w/out mount); 27 x 20.5 cm. (w/mount).
  - Item 20: Embossing, Reading [Mass.] Division, 1952; black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Gelatin silver print. Image depicts a male employee at work at an embossing machine at the Reading, Mass., division of Goodall-Sanford, Inc., of Sanford, Me. The Reading division handled dyeing and finishing. Note the large rolls of plastic fabric standing on the left. Text: "Embossing, Reading Division. Here is shown a machine which embosses plastic fabric utilizing a steel engraved plate. The designs are usually of two classes--leather-like or simulated fabric patterns." 25 x 20.5 cm. (w/out mount); 26.5 x 20.5 cm. (w/mount).
- U.S. Department of Agriculture Photographs of Wool Production, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Item 1: Display Case, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 5)
    U.S.Department of Agriculture; Negative #20397.
  - Item 2: Exhibit, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 5)
    U.S.Department of Agriculture; Negative #20398.
  - Item 3: "Finishing" Operation, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Desizing worsted cloth from loom: cloth moves fro right to left. U.S.Department of Agriculture; Negative #20399.
  - Item 4: "Finishing" Operation, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Shearing: cutting off excess lengths of fibers projecting from surface of cloth. U.S.Department of Agriculture; Negative #20400.
  - Item 5: Worsted Top Production, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Worsted cording the wool, long fibers. Producing a "ball" of card sliver. U.S.Department of Agriculture; Negative #20401.
  - Item 6: "Finishing" Operation, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Cloth measuring and folding machine. U.S.Department of Agriculture; Negative #20402.
  - Item 7: "Finishing" Operation, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Open-width dryers and cloth rolls. The white cloth is the "leader" for threading the cloth to be processed through the machine. U.S.Department of Agriculture; Negative #20403.
  - Item 8: "Finishing" Operation, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Rope (wet) scouring of cloth. U.S.Department of Agriculture; Negative #20404.
  - Item 9: Warp Prepartion: Woolen System, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Frame at extreme left supports jackspools of yarn. Yarns then go to the back reed where other special yarns are added, pass over two rolls, through a lease reed, through a reducing reed, then onto the sectin reel where the warp is made up. This would then be rewound onto a loom beam (on the further side of the section reel). U.S.Department of Agriculture; Negative #20405.
  - Item 10: "Finishing" Wool: Fulling Mills, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Note: Traps in left mill (upper section) where friction is applied to "rope" of cloth creating the heat which along with the fulling soap results in felting action. U.S.Department of Agriculture; Negative #20406.
  - Item 11: "Finishing" Operation, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Feed side. U.S.Department of Agriculture; Negative #20407.
  - Item 12: "Finishing" Operation, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Napper raising surface fibers by action of pins. U.S.Department of Agriculture; Negative #20408.
  - Item 13: Yarn Preparation: Doubler Winding, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Two yarns are wound from spinning bobbins through a tension devise and slub catcher, upward to the gathering rol, then down to the traversing yarn guide onto the tube. He two ends are wound as one. Tubes are fed to twisting where a 2-ply yarn is produced or may be fed to warper. The machine is a Foster #57 Doubler Winder. U.S.Department of Agriculture; Negative #20409.
  - Item 14: Yarn Preparation: Cone Winding, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Bobbins form spinning or twisting are placed on stationary spindles (to left of bin: see mid-machine) and yarn passes upward through a tension device and slub catcher t traversing yarn guide, then into cone which is rotated by the rum. The machine is a Folster Cone Winder. U.S.Department of Agriculture; Negative #20410.
  - Item 15: Warper, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Multiple-wound tubes are creeled behind the warper. Many ends are drawn from all the tubes to form a sheet of yans which is wound onto the warp beam. The beam may be used to feed a twister or a slasher. U.S.Department of Agriculture; Negative #20411.
  - Item 16: Worsted Yarn Preparation (Bradford System): First Rover, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 5)
    This continues the reducing of he strands. The spools from the 2-spindle Gill Box are fed into the "rover" and the strands are drafted using drafting rolls (in contrast to the pins used in gilling). Again it is wound onto double-headed wooden spools with more twist added to enable removal in the next operation. The path of the stock is downward. U.S.Department of Agriculture; Negative #20412.
  - Item 17: Worsted Yarn Preparation (Bradford System): Finisher Rover, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Spools from the First Roverr are placed in creel at the top and fed downward to the drafting rolls, drawn down t the size needed for spinning, more twist added for strength (but not enough to interfere with drafting) and then wound onto double-headed wooden spools. The path of the stock is downward. U.S.Department of Agriculture; Negative #20413.
  - Item 18: Worsted Top Preparation (Bradford System): Backwasher, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Feeds a gill box combination referred to as a backwasher gill. Cleans gilled sliver and oil for combing applied. U.S.Department of Agriculture; Negative #20415.
  - Item 19: Worsted Top Preparation (Bradford System): First Finisher Gill, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Several combed slivers are fed to gill box and combined into a sigle sliver which is then wund into a ball. This gill box produces two balls simultaneously. An additional gilling will result in "Top" (ball form) which can then be processed into yarn. U.S.Department of Agriculture; Negative #20416.
  - Item 20: Worsted Top Preparation (Bradford System): Noble Comb, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Four Gilled Slivers are wound into "punch balls" which are then placed into the Noble Comb (down low). Thes slivers are fed upward and into the feed boxes which feed the pinned "circles" (great circle (1) and small circles (20) on opposite sides of the comb. The long fibers are drawn off by verticle aprons, the strands from both sides are combined and are moved to the right and the combed sliver is coiled into a can (extreme right). U.S.Department of Agriculture; Negative #20417.
  - Item 21: Worsted Top Preparation (Bradford System): Gilling, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Open gilling: six card slivers are drawn down to one. The machine is a "gill box". It produces a ball containing the six slivers. Strand blending. U.S.Department of Agriculture; Negative #20418.
  - Item 22: Worsted Top Preparation (Bradford System): Gilling Reducer, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Gilled combed sliver from can gill is fed to the "2-Spindle Gillbox" which winds the drawn sliver onto a double-headed wooden bobbin. The weight per unit length has been reduced in this machine and a small amount of twist added to the strand to enable removal from the bobbin in the next operation. U.S.Department of Agriculture; Negative #20419.
  - Item 23: Worsted Top Preparation (Bradford System): Spinning, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 5)
    The roving is reduced to the desired size (roller drafting) and twist added to ive the desired characteristics to the yarn and wound onto a bobbin, commonly wood (without heads). This spinning frame utilizes metal caps to guide the yarn onto the bobbins. The path of the stock is dwnward. U.S.Department of Agriculture; Negative #20480.